[Music]
Stanford
University before we start we're going
to talk about Quantum chromodynamics
today Quantum chromodynamics and we're
not going to talk about the Deep
mathematics of it um and go into it we
have basically one lecture to do Quantum
Chromo Dynamics which is a huge subject
it's a subject which easily takes a
quarter uh to but I'll I'll stick with
the highlights and tell you
um what the basic intuitive picture is
quantum
chromodynamics is similar to Quantum
electrodynamics Quantum electrodynamics
is the theory of electrons and
photons it's also the theory of the
kulum force the quantum mechanical
theory of the kulum
force uh if applied to the problem of
atoms in which you do not work
about the motion or the nature of the
nucleus the structure of the nucleus you
simply think of the nucleus as a fixed
Point creating an electric field then
Quantum electrodynamics is also the
theory of
atoms and in the same sense Quantum
chromodynamics is the theory of quarks
and gluons and the theory and the things
that quarks and gluons make the things
that quarks and gluons make are called
hadrons h a d r o
NS hadrons or
hadrons and they consist of things like
protons and neutrons which are called
Barons which have a net Quirk number or
a net barion number that means an
imbalance of quirks and antiquarks three
quarks for the proton three quarks for
the
neutron and mesons which are antiquark
Pairs and all of them are full of
gluons gluons are the electrically
neutral
stuff which is the glue and The Binding
uh stuff that holds the quirks and
gluons together much the same way that
the electromagnetic field or the kulum
field is The Binding agent that holds uh
atoms together
atoms other electrostatically bound
objects all right but before we go into
it I want to remind you a little bit
about the mathematics of
spin because very first of all that
particular mathematics will come up in
another guise but also a simply related
mathematics to it will also come
up in the guise of a quantity called
color or concept called color
we're not going to do group theory in
this class all right we'll try to
finesse it but the basic um mathematics
of what we're talking about is group
Theory as I said I'm not going to use
group Theory or at least not not call it
group Theory as we use it for
the for spin the theory of spin is the
theory of a group a group group if you
don't know what a group is just ignore
it all right but the group is the group
of rotations of space the theory of spin
is also the theory of the symmetry
of physics with respect to rotations of
space but uh we finess that by not
talking about the theory of rotations
but by talking about the theory of
angular momentum I'll just remind you
very quickly that we derived everything
about angular momentum from some basic
Comm com commutation relations which
were of the form LX with l
y equal I times LZ I think there's an H
bar in there but uh yeah there is an har
in
there where those are the components of
angular momentum we worked that out last
quarter and we found some rather
surprising and interesting
things oh of course there are three
other relations like this which are
gotten by permuting X to y y to Z and Z
back to X I won't write them down but
when
we um worked out the consequences of
this first of all we broke the Symmetry
now when I say we broke the Symmetry I'm
not talking about something uh some
symmetry break in nature just we broke
the Symmetry in our mathematical
description the Symmetry being the
symmetry of rotation or the symmetry
which interchanges X Y and Z and so
forth we broke it in our heads maybe not
in the real physics but just by focusing
on the Z component of spin all right or
on the Z component of angular momentum
we basically focused on it we cannot
measure all three components
simultaneously they don't commute with
each other other here they are they
don't commute with each other at most
one of them commutes with itself of
course it commutes with itself and no
two of them commute so at most you can
talk about one of them uh or measuring
one at a time and we arbitrarily chose
LZ when we did that and used these
commutation relations what we found was
first of all that L is
quantized and the difference between
neighboring values of L
was always one
unit in units of har number
one number two we focused on a on
Spin
and we described different spin
possibilities the first set of spin
possibilities were the half spin objects
or the things which we call
Fons those were the objects whose
spin was centered about zero in such a
way that the first
level the first Z component of spin was
a half and the first one in the opposite
direction was minus a half three halves
minus three halves and so forth those
were firion but right right now the main
point was that the mathematics of spin
or angular
momentum gave rise to some multiplets
there was first this the spin half
multiplet that was the multiplet
with a spin minus a half and a spin plus
a half like the spin of the
electron that was associated with half
spin particles and
Fons bosons which for our purposes now
just think integer spin the first one
was just spin
zero there are particles with spin zero
they have no spin that's all they just
have no spin at all then there are
particles with spin one a photon is a
spin one particle there are other spin
one particles there are nuclei and atoms
of spin one and they have three
states + one minus one in units of har
bar and zero and then the next
interesting family has spin three Hales
spin three Hales again goes on the half
spin column here and that has 1/2 - 1/2
minus three
Hales uh there are particles with spin
three Hales there are certainly nuclei
with spin three
halves and atoms with spin three
halves so these things also exist
likewise what comes after spin one spin
two spin
two spin zero spin one spin minus one or
a z component of spin 1 minus one 2 and
minus two these l here are the Z
components of the spin okay now when you
speak about an object of spin
l l is the notation that denotes the
highest value of Z component of spin so
this would be or M you can use M
ordinarily it's used
M uh M or L it doesn't matter let's
let's use l let's use
l l is a little bit different than M
when you speak of spin L you're speaking
about an object whose maximum spin along
the z-axis is
L so this would be spin a half L equal a
half this one would be lals
1 and so forth okay how many states are
there how many independent states are
there for a spin a particle with spin l
2 L +
1 2 L + 1 for example a spin a half
twice
L is 1+ one is two two states if L is
one twice one is is two add one more
that's three three
states okay and so 2 L + 1 is the number
of
states is the number
independent spin
States for a given value of uh for a
given
value of L okay so that's that's
something I want you to
remember now another
thing if you have more than one particle
such as an electron
then you have two spins spins can be
combined Let's uh consider what you can
make in the way of spin by combining
together the spins of two
electrons let's forget the fact that
electrons can orbit around each other
let's ignore what's usually called
orbital angular momentum and just
concentrate on the spin angular momentum
what kind of angular momentum can you
make for two half spin
particles well the maximum
value of the Z component of spin is
what one if in units of har bar let's
forget har bar now when I say unit the
maximum spin I mean in units of har bar
the maximum spin you can have along the
z-axis is one that's when both spins are
pointing along the same when both spins
are pointing upward along the z-axis
that axis is the
z-axis right so you can have angular
momentum one you can have angular
momentum minus
one and you can also have angular
momentum or Z component of an angular
momentum zero but in fact you can have
two states where the Z component of
angular momentum is zero this one and
that
and that one this one and that one so
there are two states two independent
states whose Z component of angular
momentum is
zero how many states are there for a
spin one
object
three 2 L +
1 okay right so there must be a spin one
combination because we can make total
spin up equal to one one that's the
maximum so there must be somewhere there
a some combination must correspond to
spin
one what does a spin one have it has
spin one along the axis spin minus one
along the axis and spin zero but there
are two states with spin zero with Z
component of spin equal to zero they
can't both be part of the spin one
multiplet
what could the extra one
be it's got to
be either spin zero spin one spin two
spin three spin four spin a half spin
minor spin a half spin three
halves so here's what we found let's
let's write them
down there both spins up or both Z
components of spin I'm going to stop
saying Z components both spins up that's
got Z component equal to one both spins
down that's got Z component equal to
minus one and then there seem to be
two with Z component equal to
zero but if I look at spin one it all
all it has is plus minus and
zero there are only three of them so
this cannot be a multipli this these
four states cannot all correspond to
spin
one what else could be there besides
one spin zero can't be spin two because
spin two has to have five space
States the only other thing is spin zero
so there must be Quantum States here
three Quantum States corresponding to
spin one
and one when you put the spins together
and you ask what kind of angular
momentum can you make you can make spin
one and spin zero the only combination
the only question is what combination
what quantum mechanical combination of
these two correspond to spin zero and
what combination correspond to spin one
to the missing spin worm combination and
I will tell you right now the answer is
that the symmetric combination with a
plus
sign incidentally this state over here
is symmetric between interchange you can
think of it if you like as one spin over
here one spin over here they're labeled
there the one over here and the one over
here the spin States if they're both up
is symmetric that means the spin state
is the same if you interchange the two
spins obviously they're both up this one
is also
symmetric up down by itself is not
symmetric if you interchange spin if you
interchange the two of them this one
goes to this one and this one goes to
this one they swamp but there's one
linear combination one quantum
mechanical
combination which is symmetric Under The
Interchange of the two plus minus plus
minus
plus this is the symmetric State what
should you do to it to make it have
total probability equal to one
/ it by the sare < TK of
two these are the three states which
together form 0 1 and minus
one if you rotate the axes they
transform into each other this is a spin
one up this is a spin one down where's
the ones with spin one in the other
directions it's made up out of
this okay so this is the spin one
multiplet and what about the other one
we missing a state there were four all
together here we have three linear
combinations what's the other linear
combination the the other orthogonal
linear
combination with a minus one so there's
another one here with up down
minus down up
over Square < TK of
two this one this is these three
correspond to Lal 1 this one corresponds
to L equals 0 so these are the ways that
you can put two spin halfes together to
make the two possible
combinations this combination L equals z
what is it like with respect to its
angular momentum the answer it doesn't
have any angular momentum it's a thing
without angular
momentum as far as angular momentum goes
it's like a nothing I mean it may have
some energy it may have other things
charge whatever but as far as angular
momentum goes it's like empty space it's
got none okay uh you might ask can a
upspin and a down spin come together and
annihilate and disappear well there's
all kinds of reasons why electrons can't
disappear but just for Ang pure angular
momentum re
reasons if we just worried about
conservation of angular momentum and
nothing
else then which of these combinations
can just disappear if as I said if we
worried about nothing but angular
momentum
conservation can this
disappear no because it has two units of
angular momentum up how about
down how about this one one yes or no
let's take a vote how many think yes how
many think no okay the nose win because
this one is not without angular
momentum it looks like it has no Z
component of angular momentum and it
doesn't but the angular momentum about
the X and Y AIS of this is not equal to
zero it does not have Lal 0 it has Lal 1
this is the missing thing that allows
you to rotate the angle momentum into
other directions what about this
one yeah that one has angular momentum
zero and if it if the only consideration
was angular momentum conservation it
could Decay it could just disappear now
one way of thinking about it is you
could say
well um yeah that's good enough that's
that's uh that's that's close enough
this one here can disappear
okay so if you were to measure the
angular momentum of the symmetric one
with respect to Z You' get one or minus
one yeah uh
wa in in which case in the symmetric
case no you get with along the z- axis
you would get zero in either case z yeah
along the z-axis but if you measure the
angular momentum along some other
axis you would get one or minus
one all right so that's that's the
theory of angular momentum now why am I
bringing that up now or the theory of
spin in particular spin a half spin a
half and how you build out of it other
spins oh
incidentally uh let's build let's try to
build spin three halves let's ask what
happens if you put
together um
three
spins well if they're all pointing
upward in the same direction what's uh
and that would be the maximum what would
you get three halves how many states are
there with spin three
halves oh incidentally how many states
are there all together of
uh of three spins each with spin a
half
eight 2 * 2 * 2
two okay so there are eight states all
together how many states are there
uh for um a spin three haves object four
four so how many left
over four what can those other four be
could they be another spin three Hales
object
no why
not be zero on other ax okay so let's
let's let's go through it again if you
have a spin 3 has multiplet there will
be one state which has Z component of
spin 3 Hales and one with minus three
Hales we've already used those up when
we said there were four states which
formed the spin three Hales multiplet we
use them up now all that's left now is
spins whose maximum value is plus or
minus a
half okay so what can be there what an
addition can be
there only spin only spin
uh spin one half anything
else could it be no they can't be spin
zero because making three spinner halves
can never make spin
zero all it can make is spin three
halves and spin
one2 but we seem to have four states
left over the implication is there are
two distinct ways to make spin
1/2 so there are
combinations which correspond to the
spin three halves the easiest ones are
all three spins up or three spins down
and then there were more complicated
ones and then there are two distinct
ways to make spin 1/2 which altogether
adds up to four states all right so when
you take three spins three half spins
you get spin three halves and you get
spin one half twice two distinct ways of
doing
it let's keep that in
mind okay now why am I talking about
spin now what I really want to talk
about is a concept called isos spin
isotopic spin isotopic spin was the
first internal symmetry group that
or the first internal quantum number the
first analog of a spin which occurred in
particle physics that did not have to do
with the rotation of space but it had to
do with the rotation of an imaginary
space or an internal space or if you
like it just gave rise to another set of
quantum mechanical variables which were
basically isomorphic completely similar
to spin to spin a to spin but it didn't
have to do with spin it didn't have to
do with the rotation of space you could
imagine if you like that it had to do
with the rotation of some internal
directions internal directions imaginary
directions of space uh mathematical
directions so let me tell you where it
comes from we've already actually
described it although we haven't said
it we talked about
quirks and we talked about there a whole
variety of different kinds of
quirks but most of the quirks were
rather
heavy they were rather heavy uh and had
an appreciable mass in
units of gevs or hundreds of Ms the
natural Mass scale for hadron physics is
somewhere as hundreds of
Ms the mass of a typical Meson is a
couple of hundred MS
The Binding energy of particles is Ms
Mill uh sorry hundreds of Ms not Ms
hundreds of Ms what object in nature has
binding energies of water a few
Ms
nuclei nuclei nuclei things that hold
protons and neutrons together but what
holds a neutron together as three quarks
has a binding energy of a few hundred me
all right so the the Natural Energy
scale is a few hundred
me and there were only two quirks which
were very light but or whose masses were
very light by comparison with that and
they were the up quark and the down
Quark the other quarks are heavy and to
make particles out of them there's a
cost in energy and so for the lightest
objects the most stable typically
heavier objects will Decay the lighter
ones the light objects of Nuclear
Physics the lightest objects and the
ones which are stable are the ones made
of up and down quirks now up and down
quirks have almost the same mass of
course the down Quirk is about twice as
heavy as the up Quark but they both have
very small mass by comparison with the
hundreds of Ms of uh of nuclear physics
so in some first
approximation you can say that the up
quark and the down quark
have no Mass their ma more important
their masses are close to being
equal that's a symmetry what does that
mean that means if you took all up
quarks and replaced them by all down
quarks everything would be pretty
similar now of course the up Quark is
slightly more massive than the down no
the down Quark is slightly more massive
than the up Quark so typically things
made of down quirks will be a little
more heavy than the things made of the
corresponding up quirks but the
difference is small for
example uh two up quirks and a down
Quirk make a proton two down quirks and
an up Quirk make a neutron the mass
difference between a neutron and a
proton is very
small okay uh so that's an example of
the almost symmetry between up quirks
and down
quirks so in approximation you just
forget the difference up quirks and down
quirks are symmetric with respect to
each other in the same way or in the
mathematically the same way that a spin
up and a spin down are
symmetric in the case of spin it really
has to do with the symmetry of space
rotating the axes in the case of uh
of up quirks and down quirks it's just a
mathematical uh manufactured space that
you can imagine where you take an up
Quark to a down Quark by flipping some
direction in some imaginary Direction in
your head but all you're doing is
interchanging up quirks and down
quirks thinking of up quirks and down
quirks is
mathematically the same or
mathematically isomorphic to up spins
and down spins you come to the concept
of isotopic
spin isotop IC spin is the analog of
spin but not up and down in the sense of
the zaxis and the flipping spin but up
and down in the sense of up quirks and
down quirks because there's nothing
really up up up or down about it it's
just the interchange of two labels up
quirks and down
quirks and so when invin the concept of
isotopic
spin
uh and for all mathematical purposes the
replacement of up quarks and down quirks
is very analogous to the replacement by
of an up spin by a down
spin okay
so for spin we have two states up and
down and that defines
spin for quirks we have up and down and
that defines
isospin incidentally what does this
where does the iso come
from
isotope isotope we're going to see in a
moment that isotopic spin
interchanges same when when you
interchange up quirks and down quirks
you interchange proton and
neutron of course if you interchange
proton and neutron in the nucleus you'll
wind up making an isotope of some uh of
something so it comes from the word
isotope uh isotopic span but what it is
is in nuclear physics in the old days it
was just the replacement or The
Interchange of a proton by a neutron and
thinking of the proton and
neutron as um a spin multiplet in a
mathematical spin space it was traced
eventually just to the fact that there
were two quirks up quirks and down
quirks that was the origin of it yeah
did I supin predate uh oh
yeah go to
Heisenberg yeah well something has to
provide the extra charge or yeah okay
so isotopic spin is not a precise
symmetry of
nature it's not a precise symmetry of
nature in that first of all the UPC Cork
and down cork don't have exactly the
same mass but even if they did there
would still be a distinction a physical
distinction which uh would be which
would make them different and that is
their electric charge
all right electric forces within the
nucleus except for a big nucleus when a
nucleus gets big electro electric forces
become strong but for small nuclei and
especially for protons and neutrons and
hadrons electromagnetic forces are
negligible by comparison with the other
forces holding protons and neutrons
together so an approximation ignore the
mass difference between protons and
neutrons
or ignore the mass difference between up
quarks and down quarks and ignore the
fact that they have electric charge
altoe and concentrate on the other
forces of nature in particular the
strong interaction forces which will
come to and
then there is a precise symmetry
relating up quirks the down quirks and
that symmetry is very much like ordinary
spin symmetry it is analogous to spin
symmetry
okay let's talk about what you can make
supposing
uh well one Quirk by itself we will come
to understand is not a physical object
that we can examine in the
laboratory the simplest object that we
can examine in the laboratory is three
quarks and that's a proton or a
neutron that's like having three
spins what can you make out of three
spins okay well what you can make out of
three spins is either spin three halves
or spin one/ half and you can make the
spin one/ half in two distinct ways but
let's forget the two ways let's just say
we can make spin three halves and spin
one half in the same way taking three
quarks we can make an object of isotopic
spin one2 or an object of isotopic spin
three Hales let's first concentrate on
the object of isotopic spin
1/2 an object of isotopic spin 1/2 how
many states should it have just by pure
mathematical analogy with ordinary
spin two a spin a half object has two
states an isospin is isospin is the
right is the simplified word an isospin
state
of uh one half also would have two
states what are those two states
proton and
neutron
uh so let's uh write down what the
proton and neutron are in Quark language
now let's uh let's that's that's a
that's proton okay let's imagine that
we've labeled
the the quirks by label the quirks let's
imagine they're really located at three
distinct spots inside the proton this of
course is not really true but I mean
they move around but let's just simplify
the story and say there are three
distinct quirks and we're we're going to
label them uh with three distinct
labels here's a down quark and here's
two up quirks all right the down Quirk
might be the Quirk at position
one all right so let's call it at
position one the up Quark might be at
position
two and the U the other UPC might be at
three is there anything wrong with this
state
Quark aerons
right quar aerion because because quirks
are
Fons their states should be
anti-symmetric their states should be
anti-symmetric okay now that suggests
that maybe the right combination for the
ukor is to anti- symmetrize it and that
would be correct
that's not an important uh issue for us
right now but I'm just being very
precise that a down Quirk and two up
quirks in an anti-symmetric
State uh is a
proton an anti-symmetric state of two
spins makes spin
zero so this is an isospin zero object
times an isospin a half object that has
isospin a half but never mind this is
this this is a bit of mathematics it's a
little too fancy we don't need to worry
about it this is the proton it has
charge +
one two sorry 2/3 plus
2/3 is 4/3 and minus A3 makes charge one
so that's the proton and it is the
combination of three quirks which makes
an isospin a half State same as three
spins making a spin a half state so the
proton is also a member of a spin isos
spin a half object and the other one is
gotten by simply interchanging ups and
downs and that's up down down let me not
uh let me not belabor this point about
the Symmetry here and that's the
neutron the proton and the neutron in
this language are symmetric with respect
to each other and they form an isotopic
spin a half double
it okay in the same sense that you can
put three spins together to make a spin
a half and there are only two
such States so isotopic
spin
invades the theory of protons and
neutrons and in this language just gives
us another just like the Quark has
isotopic spin a half so does the neutron
and
proton
okay there's another object which is
very similar to a proton and neutron in
many ways it's also made of three
quarks but it's the
combination oh incidentally what is the
spin of the proton and neutron actual
spin 1/2
okay so you take you've taken three
quirks with the same
spin sorry three quarks with Spin and
three quarks with isos Spin and you've
made a spin a half and an isos spin a
half okay now there's another object
which has three quirks in it which
has um
spin three Hales and isos spin three
Hales if you like the three ordinary
spins are lined up in it in the same
direction and the three ISO spins are
lined up so what kind of thing are they
well if the three isos spins are lined
up that must mean that there are objects
with three up
quarks three up quirks three down
quirks
also the three spins are aligned just
the ordinary spins the three spins are
also aligned to form spin three
Hales or down or whatever three quarks
up three quarks three up quarks or three
down quirks this is not a neutron this
doesn't this is not a neutron or a
proton this is a new object which is a
little bit more massive than a proton
and neutron it has a name it's called
the
Delta it has isospin three
Hales and it has spin three Hales so
it's sometimes called the Delta three
Hales it has both isospin and spin three
Hales let's forget its spin its spins
are just aligned we line them up all
along the z-axis then they're all
aligned let's forget
that what about this can this be all
there is to an isos spin 3al
State how many states does an does a
spin three Hales object
have four right so there must be two
more and there are two more there are
two more Delta 3 half
States two more of them and the two more
are are
uu and u
d four
states four objects all of which are
related by symmetries they all have very
close to the same mass the only thing
which distinguishes their mass is the
little small difference between masses
of up and down quirks and they're all
very similar to each other I'm telling
you this for a reason this this played
an important historical role that I'm
going to tell you about in a moment
uh these four states are called the
Delta 3 Hales and what's their charges
let's go through their charges what's
the charge of this
one excuse me what's the difference
between U and
duu all right let's work that the
charges pardon let's
work what the third one down what's the
difference between that and the proton
ah spin spin spin spin three halves not
spin one2 uhoh okay yeah the isos spin
is the Z compon though no it has it's
part of the multiplet which is an isos
spin three Hales
object okay right isos spin three Hales
right so has both Spin and isos spin
three halves but by looking at these two
you couldn't tell that you have to know
you have to know a bit more about the
nature of the way they're combined all
right but bottom to the bottom to SP one
half are they not no they have a
component of isos spin just as the
analog of the Z component of spin would
be
1/2 but the full isotopic spin would be
three
halves
yeah remember every object which has a
spin three halves comes in four
states four states here they
[Music]
are
12us -
3es -
3 same is true for
isospin okay but let's concentrate on
spin for a
moment
uh these two
states
they that's these
two and the ones of Maximum and minimum
spin that's these two
so it's got to be four of them we know
that a thing with spin three halves has
four
states Z component of
isospin can be 1/2 and minus
one2
but by analogy with ordinary spin there
will have to be four of them okay but
let's uh let's come to the
uh uh to the important
points let's first of all label their
charges this one has three charge two3
object it has charge
two this one has
charge minus
one and uu has charge + one and charge
what is this one
zero so the charges
are different well they these two do
have the same charges uh sorry did I get
this
right uu no yeah yeah yeah these do
happen to have the same charge as proton
and and neutron but these are different
okay all four of these objects have to
within a small discrepancy the same mass
just as the proton and neutron have the
same mass these have the same mass but
that mass is not the same as the proton
and
neutron proton and neutron the
mass is about
940 in units of Ms millions of electron
volts this is the mass of the proton and
neutron with the neutron being slightly
heavier not by much
okay the mass of the
delta is about 1,200
me the Delta can Decay it can Decay into
a proton and a neutron and a Pon let's
just see how that would
work let's take uh the the easy ones the
easy ones have all three quirks the same
up up up so here we have three up quirks
moving
along and how can that de
what is what is it going to Decay into
it's going to Decay into a Proton or
Neutron and a Meson a Meson is a quark
anti- Quark pair let me just draw for
you how this happens this would be up up
up the two up quirks go
off this up Quark also goes off but
quarks can't separate like that
quark and an antiquark appear in
between like
that the quark and the anti- Quark in
between could either be a down Quark or
an up
Quark so one possibility is that this is
another up quark and then this would be
an anti-up quark and this would be an up
Quark an up quark and an anti-up Quark
have zero
charge this would be the decay of the
Delta 3 Hales
what do we have here this one uh no this
one can't
happen this one actually can't Decay not
possible we have to put a down Quirk
here there's just not enough energy for
it to happen this would be an anti- down
Quirk and an up Quirk so what would this
thing be up up and
down that would be a
proton the proton is lighter than the
delta
so there's enough left over energy how
much energy is left
over let's see 260 me about right
something like that 300 meev roughly 300
me what's the mass of a
Pion about
140 about 140 M so there's enough energy
for this to happen and still leave over
some kinetic energy for the pon to fly
away what what kind of Pon is
this with an up and a down
[Music]
bar what's its
charge 2/3 and 1/3 so this is a
pi+ and a proton total charge two this
is the object with charge two so these
Delta objects are not stable they all
can Decay into a Proton or Neutron and a
Pon and they're very
shortlived their lifetime oh we could
work out the numeric I'll tell you what
their lifetime is order of magnitude
order of magnitude it's the time that
light would take to cross the
proton so you can figure out that proton
is about 10 Theus 13
cm uh what's the speed of light 10 to
the 10th centim per second
so 10 Theus 23rd seconds or something
they don't last long but they do last
long enough to be
identifiable as distinct objects uh when
they're produced these Deltas these
deltas and collisions particle
collisions Deltas are produced and
they're real objects but they're very
very short-lived excuse me uh as a
matter of notation does it make any
difference which order you put using
these no not not for not for purpose is
here
no
no you have have time you have down and
you have the two
up again you have the
upart they're F on so they can't be in
the same state okay that's exactly what
we have to come to now all right there's
something wrong here something's rotten
in the state of
Denmark
um what is it
well we have three up
quirks Whose
spins are all in the same direction we
could put those spins we could if we
like choose those spins to be all up and
make a Delta three halves with its spin
ordinary spin up with all three in the
same direction and they' all be three up
quirks you're not allowed to put two
Fons in the same state
uh if um if you could fiddle around with
a
spin maybe you could do something with a
spin but all the three spins are the
same why are they the same because it
has spin three Hales three quarks with
spin three Hales have the same spin they
also have the same isos spin namely
they're all up quirks so we seem to have
found an object which consists of three
identical
upks that's a
violation of the principle that you
cannot put two firion into the same
state this was the clue that led
eventually to what is called Quantum
chromodynamics it was realized that
quirks have to have another
property they must have another
property uh so that the three quarks in
the Delta 3 Hales can be different from
each other the firon statistics the
fironic property of them requires that
they be different so there must be a
label another label that was hidden from
view for some reason which
um which is
there but not apparent in
experiments that label is called color
color is again highly arbitrary term it
has nothing whatever to do with ordinary
color and it was just a label to uh
to uh
to a name a
name different in different uh
places the three colors of quirks are
different in some places they're red
white and blue mostly in the southern
parts of the United States
other places are red green and
blue red green and blue being the
primary colors of
light that you see with your
eyes I will use red green and
blue I haven't heard red white and blue
being used for a long time not the for
the last nine years or
so but they're just labels they're just
labels and in no sense are they
physically different one from another in
any sort of interesting measurable way
the fact that there are three distinct
ones and that they are that they are not
the same is important they have exactly
the same mass they have exactly the same
properties so let's now write down what
we know about the uh the labeling of
quirks all the various quirks we know
about there
are up quirks down quirks
those that's the lightest one and there
are Charmed quarks strange
quarks and after charm comes top
quarks and bottom quarks they're not
listed in order of mass the up is the
lightest the down is next the charm is
much heavier than the strange by a
factor of about eight or something like
that and the top is vastly heavier than
the bottom but I've just put them in
I've been perverse and put up on top of
down I don't know
why
uh these are the six distinct types of
quirks but now for each type of
Quirk there is another
label so quirks are labeled by two
labels and the two labels are
red
green and blue
as I said I don't want anybody to think
they're really red green and blue but
that's the
label and where did that come from how
did we know it was there well it's one
of these things where physicists simply
followed their noses they simply said
look there's something wrong with this
Quark model you can't have three quarks
all in the same state they must differ
by something else now they could differ
by position but it was known that for
one reason or another that it didn't
have to do with position and
momentum uh that was that was known to
be Irrelevant for dynamical reasons for
energetic reasons so that was not the
issue there were three quirks all in the
same state they must have a in in fact
the situation was actually quite similar
to what happened in atomic physics spin
was discovered
by ulach and GMI because of the uh
because of atomic
spectroscopy helium had two electrons in
the same
state no good violates the the PO
principle well actually the timing here
I think may be a little bit confused but
it could have worked this way they could
have said well poy tells us that you
can't put two things in that maybe it
did work that I can't remember now I
wasn't around I don't remember uh but
the the reason or one of the reasons
that gout smmi and embeck might have
since I don't know the history in detail
might have invented spin was because in
the helium atom there were two electrons
apparently in the same orbital state so
you've got to attach to the hel to the
electron another quantum number another
um uh
label and that worked that worked just
fine it worked a second time his hisory
repeated itself and various people nambo
nambo was the one who realized this yero
nambo uh nambu the Japanese physic
Japanese American physicist uh nambo
realized that this called for another
quantum number and he said every Quark
has to have another degree of freedom I
don't think he called it color I suspect
that was Gman but I'm not sure many but
a good time a good deal later and then
what he said is look all that's going on
here is that you've put three quarks
together one red one green and one blue
and now you're in
business no more violation of the
Heisenberg uncertainty principle the
same trick incidentally works for
protons and
neutrons
uh that uh you can understand the proton
and neutron also as a red what am I what
are my colors again red green and blue
those are the primary colors yes yeah a
question so is there a physical property
that can be measured or no no in every
possible way they are the
same except we know there are three
distinct ones so if you had one you
could tell the other why I mean how can
you say there are how can you say that
maybe the you know principle doesn't
apply which
huh if you can't detect the difference
right you can if you have one you can
tell the other one's different from how
what are you measuring or uh that's
that's uh that's a little bit
complicated and uh in collisions you can
tell that if you have one if you have
two of them you can tell that they can't
be the same that you can
tell couldn't you in uh aren't they
conserved in the color conserved so in
theaction you have might be a different
color well yeah the color is conserved
but it's also always zero it's not only
conserved but it's always zero so it's a
little bit funny conservation
law but look you could say the same
thing about cusion doesn't quite tell
you uh that you need all three of the
colors for a uu say it
again no but you need do need something
to distinguish the two U's right yeah
but it gives you more than you need in
that case yeah it gives you more than
you need that's why that's why
historically the Delta 3 Hales played an
important role it was looking at this
guy here which was unambiguous three
quarks parallel spin par parallel
isospin something's wrong it would have
been possible to analyze the protons and
neutrons but it would have been less
convincing when the Delta 3 halves was
interpreted in terms of quirks that
really hit you over the head that
uh uh
so the ultimate resolution is we now
know you know really experiment mentally
extremely well that the three quirks uh
that three different kinds of colors are
really
there you know even with ordinary
spin what's the difference between Spin
up this way and spin that way there's no
difference they have exactly the same
property all you have to do is turn your
head
over uh or spin this way unless you have
another one to set a direction or
something to set a
direction then uh then you can't tell
the difference between them on the other
and if you have some object which picks
out a direction and you bring a spin up
to it you can tell whether the spin is
along a particular Axis or not in the
same way if you have a
proton a
proton being different than a neutron
and the proton and the neutron are
identifiable objects I mean in the
laboratory if you have a proton it picks
out a Direction in this isospin sta
space it's up in the isospin direction
not down then if you have another Quark
you can discover whether that Quirk is
par has its isospin parallel to or
anti-parallel to the proton so yes you
can tell not it's isospin you can tell
whether
it's I said something wrong um but close
enough
if you have one object it can provide a
kind of frame of reference for the other
ones and test whether they're the same
or not um but the mathematics of quantum
chromodynamics simply
requires that uh that you have these
three different things you could say
maybe it's a violation of the POI
principle um you could there's no known
mathematical framework for for
discussing that and there's no Quantum
field theory that has anything but fans
and bons so you'd have to invent
something
new yeah I thought these the U theor
principle involes
observable and you know like momentum
position and you can make a case that
isospin is a kind of Observer absolutely
what would be the appropriate observable
for
color much much more subtle much more
subtle much more subtle
um let's come back to it I'll tell you
when we get the after we've talked a
little bit
about question it was known that quarks
are Fons because of their skin of the
proton
which is that how they M okay yeah I
guess I have the same question in
different form if you have a a down up
up a proton M um one of them one of the
three quarks is green and since the down
there's only one
of I mean the question the question is
how can you really associate with one
color with one of the qus no you have to
think of quantum superpositions of
States so you might write
let's take the case of the
proton up down down this could be green
red
blue
but we have to
write all
possibilities all ways of combining them
and uh to make a real proton so we have
to use some quantum mechanics to
symmetrize the wave functions and so
forth symmet rze and anti- symmetrize
them
appropriately but the uh the big
advantage of this Delta 3 halves is you
didn't have to do anything fancy just
the three all in the same
direction no okay um sure you could say
well maybe there was something wrong
with our ideas about Quantum field
Theory but by
now
the theory of quantum chromodynamics
which is exactly B Chromo has to do with
color color is the important quantity in
Quantum chromodynamics just like charge
is the important quantity in uh in
electrodynamics
um this theory is a highly accurate uh
description of experimental data
associated with the Collision of uh of
hadrons and its accuracy is you know Way
Beyond what can be questioned now so the
ultimate answer is that it
works okay now let's talk about gluons
the missing ingredient now we have the
analog of
electrons the quirks the
Fons they have some attributes they have
some electric
charge like electrons they stick
together not quite the way
um electrons stick to a nucleus perhaps
a little more the way electrons stick to
positrons but they stick together some
somehow what's
missing is what sticks them together
what sticks together
atoms is uh the electrostatic field the
electrostatic field is associated with
photons we can either think of it in
field language that every electron
creates a field around it or we can
think of it in particle language that
electrons Emit and absorb photons the
exchange of photons back and forth
between charged particles creates the
um uh the forces between them what about
quirks what sticks them
together particles very very similar to
the uh to the
photon at first it was a speculation
maybe such objects exist then a theory
was built a mathematical theory was
built with quarks and gluons gluons
being the analog of photon they're very
similar to photons they have spin one
just like the
photon which means they have the same
kind of polarization States they're
massless like
photons very similar but with one big
difference that will come
to and they jump back and forth or they
well on the one hand a quirk is a
source of the field that's associated
with gluons the gluon field in the same
same sense that the electron is the
source of the electromagnetic field on
the other hand not the other hand but
similar hand the um quirks can Emit and
absorb
gluons what are gluons like what
quantities do gluons have photons are
pretty in a certain sense uninteresting
except for the fact that they have a
polarization they have a spin they have
a
polarization uh they have a momentum and
they have a polarization and that's
about all they don't have any
charge by itself a
photon if it collides with another
Photon there are no forces now that's
not exactly
true there are forces between photons
but they're secondary effects they're
not electrostatic forces because the
photon is charged there are secondary
effects which come from quantum
electrodynamics and Loops of uh Quant
complicated finding diagrams involving
electrons but the primordial interaction
between photons is there is none they
move freely past each other and that's
why a beam of light moving in One
Direction will pass will pass through a
beam of light moving in the other
direction with no interaction except
unless you're in some
material okay so photons are not very
interesting and in the sense that they
don't interact with each other they are
interesting from the point of view of
their interaction with electrons and
basically all of quantum electrodynamics
is summarized by one diagram and that
diagram which we've drawn several times
is the emission of a photon from an
electron
electrons are drawn as having a
directionality the direction along which
the charge is moving you can flip lines
around and every time you see an arrow
going downward that indicates a pro a
positron but it's all one basic vertex
that's it and out of that you can build
forces you can build uh collisions
everything
else right just for the purposes of
um
bookkeeping think of a photon as having
the same
charge as an electron and a positron in
fact a photon if it's given a a hit and
given a little extra energy can Decay
into an electron and a positron it's not
that in any sense a photon is made of an
electron and a positron that's not the
point but it happens to have the same
properties as an electron and a positron
in particular its electric
charge uh it also has a angular momentum
it has a spin a spin of one and with an
electron and positron if you line up
their spins you can also make a spin of
one so in many ways a photon
is similar to an electron and a positron
that's sometimes indicated by drawing by
thinking of the photon as a fictitious
composite of an electron and a
positron and then this diagram this
diagram of the emission of a photon can
be
drawn just by saying
the electron comes
along becomes an electron over here the
electron over here was really a positron
moving backward which turned around now
there's no content in this other than to
say without losing any electric charge
you can emit a photon and you can see it
directly you don't really you certainly
don't need this to see that an electron
can emit a photon and that there's no
violation of charge conservation that's
totally obvious that an electron can
emit an electrically neutral thing but
uh nevertheless let's just draw the
emission of a photon by thinking of the
photon as a composite of an electron and
positron it's it's not useful for
electrodynamics the analog is quite
useful for Quantum Chromo
Dynamics okay now let's come to
quirks
electrons were finished with and the
important thing in Quantum
chromodynamics is the color so let's
begin with quirks quirks can be red
green or
blue let's make a column Vector out of
them and use the language of quantum
mechanics a quark can either be in the
red State the Green State or the blue
State and make a column out of it okay
an antiquark let's represent
antiquarks by Red Bar Green
Bar and blue
[Music]
bar a
gluon first of all a gluon is an object
that can be emitted by a quark if this
is a
quark and a quirk goes off a gluon can
be emitted
but the interesting thing is the gluon
behaves in some respects like a quark
and an
antiquark it's not a quirk and an
antiquark we we'll I'll tell you
precisely in what sense it behaves like
a quark and an antiquark but let's think
of the
gluon as a quark and an antiquark in the
same
way so how do we label if we label each
Quark by a color
this now becomes a quark and an anti-
Quark a quark and an antiquark how many
different kinds of quirks and antiquarks
are
there
what did I hear nine yeah okay you're
almost
right right the logic was what I was
looking for I wanted you to say
nine um there's a subtlety there's a
subtlety which will come to there are
really only
eight but
uh uh but let's say nine to begin with
what are those nine quarks well sorry
what are those nine gluons they're the
nine combinations that you can make by
taking a quark and an antiquark in other
words they make a
matrix if quarks are like a column then
and we might think of uh just for fun we
might think of antiquarks as making a
row Red Bar Green green bar Blue Bar
then
gluons would fill out a
matrix all right in other words to label
a gluon you would label it with two
indices two colors and what would there
be there would be red red
bar red green
bar red blue
bar
green red
bar green green bar
green blue bar what
else BR R
Bar B G
Bar B bar bar so the diagonals are
interesting say it again the diagonal
elements are
indistinguishable well the diagonal
elements are not really
indistinguishable but the but the point
is that the sum of the diagonal elements
is uh uh
is not an independent Quantum
State all right so it would seem like
there are nine
gluons later on we will talk about a
particular subtlety which tells us the
quantum mechanical superposition of red
red bar plus green green bar plus blue
blue bar is a nothing doesn't exist but
for now for our purposes right now let's
neglect that there are really only eight
gluons but it really does look from this
pattern here that there should be nine
so let's let's play with it as if there
were
nine uh then what uh kind of Fineman
diagrams can exist well a quirk can
become another kind of Quirk and emit a
gluon right so let's draw the diagram
for that let's take the case of a red
Quark becoming a green quark
and emitting a glue on what kind of glue
on gets
emitted
red green
bar where's red green bar
here right
here red green bar and if you like you
can draw that with a neat
notation uh the notation is just a
bookkeeping device really and here here
it's useful here it really is useful
just think of the red is going through
and the green also is going through
except when you flip the green line over
it becomes an anti- green and a
red so the gluon that's emitted is as if
the red just went through and the green
annihilated a green
bar that's the basic vertex of quantum
chromodynamics there's not just one of
them there are nine of them or actually
only eight but uh but the pattern is
quirk goes to another kind of quark and
a gluon is
emitted if a red quk goes to a red Quark
then it's a red red bar if a red Quark
goes to a blue Quark then it's a red
blue bar and so forth and so
on okay
now that's as I said the basic uh the
basic
phenomenon or
the basic primitive building block of
quantum
chromodynamics you can build all sorts
of sorry that's half that's one of the
building
blocks there is another building block
that isn't there for Quantum
electrodynamics as I said photons don't
interact with each other in particular a
photon can't emit a photon and another
Photon electron can emit a photon and
stay an electron photons don't emit
photons so photons don't interact with
each other in any way except uh in
materials excuse me yeah uh gluons are
only emitted with a change of
qu no they can uh no you can have uh
they don't have to change the quar no I
mean
this
process and whether it changes or
whether do not changed neveress this is
the only method where which one emits a
gluon that's right this is the only way
in which gluons are emitted but there is
something new that makes Quantum
chromodynamics first of all far more
complicated and far more interesting
than electrodynamics
let's take a gluon moving along here's a
gluon let's see let's take that gluon to
be
a
uh
red blue bar
gluon it's a red blue bar
gluon okay now can this happen I'm going
to show you something that yes is really
part of quantum
chromodynamics maybe it's not too Sur
surprising once I draw it this is not
really a quirk but just imagine it's a
fictitious Quark making up the gluon all
right fictitious Quark goes off well if
it's a fictitious Quark it better not
really go off but we'll see in a moment
what happens to it and the blue bar
keeps
going but
now if these really were quirks a quirk
and an antiquark could form what kind of
quark and antiquark would you like to
put
there green
let's put green
there this would be green going this way
and this would be anti-green going this
way and this would be red so red goes
through Blue Bar goes through and green
becomes anti-green going that way well
what do we have now now we have a basic
vertex in which three gluons come
together let's draw gluons as wavy lines
similar to uh to photons we now have a
vertex in which a red blue
bar becomes a red green bar and a green
blue
bar we don't really have to remember
what combinations are possible all we
have to do is figure out which diagrams
we can draw
where all of the lines go through where
without being
interrupted you can figure out what the
various uh couplings or what the various
possible fundamental diagrams there are
connecting uh gluons this is the new
thing what it means is that gluons
interact with each other gluons exert
forces on gluons in a way that would be
Unthinkable for photons photons cannot
exchange photons between them gluons can
exchange gluons between them so now
let's come to
forces the gluon behaves in a way which
is similar to the photon and does
something which is similar to what the
photon
does it can be
exchanged here's a
diagram it's easy to draw diagrams where
quirks interact with each other all
right let's let's draw yeah let's draw a
diagram in which an antiquark interacts
with a
quark all right here's a blue
bar
antiquark which
emits a Blue
Bar
Green
gluon becomes a green
gluon and now the green Glon the green
what sorry let's see this would be a
green bar this would be a blue green bar
gluon all right here green
bar is blue but let's say that
blue goes right through like that and
what do we have here we have here now an
exchange of a gluon between a blue bar
and a blue making a green bar and a
green that's a kind of force
between quir
s that creates a force between quirks in
very much the same way that
photons exchanged between electrons
create
forces uh you might want to make a force
between a blue bar and a blue bar
supposing we
wanted force between a blue bar and a
blue then we would make this blue bar
here all right so we can make all sorts
of forces this way
but what about forces between gluons all
we have to do to this diagram is add an
extra two lines let's what did I have
this originally
um blue blue bar let's make it blue
bar and green bar up
here green up
here let's put another line in
here it's not another Quirk now it's
really going to be representing a gluon
and this one let's take to be
red red goes right
through let's put another line over here
I don't know what did I take that one to
be I think I took that one to be blue
bar blue
bar this is now a diagram which
represents the exchange of a gluon
between two
gluons this is really something new this
is something very very different than
electrodynamics
what does it lead to it leads to forces
between
gluons quirks can bind
together because of the exchange of
gluons and make hadrons but gluons can
bind together and make objects there are
objects in Quantum chromodynamics which
contain no quirks there are no bound
objects there are no bound States
composite objects in Quantum
electrodynamics just made up out of
photon
there are objects which are just made up
out of gluons and how do they happen
they happen
because gluons can exchange gluons back
and forth we could just summarize this
by
saying there's a force due to the
exchange of gluons between
gluons uh this would also mean for
example that if you had two waves of
gluons going going past each
other they would interact with each
other they would deform each other they
wouldn't just go through each other just
like two electromagnetic waves in fact
even if you had a single gluon wave
moving along the different parts of it
would exert forces on each other and
cause it to deform or do whatever it
might
do
so the watch word is that the Dynamics
of gluons is
nonlinear yeah do we have to have the
same number of uh Reds greens and blues
that uh you just have to make sure the
lines follow through the diagram
uninterrupted well that's what this
that's what the following the lines
means where did I did I draw this wrong
I might have drawn this oh sorry this
should be green bar this should be green
Bar Green uh green bar yeah sorry the
rule is follow the lines when a line
turns around in time like that change it
to an
antiparticle and that's basically the
Only Rule of quantum chromodynamics that
there
are interactions between quirks and
gluons and
they they um satisfy the let's call it
the follow the line rule
right and there are interactions between
gluons and gluons and they also Follow
The Line Rule still have an
anti anti color problem with
RGS let's see
where
RG oh sorry
RG
that's R Bar Bar this should be B
bar and that be
G should be bar that's right going this
way this one should be G and this one
should be G bar okay let's draw let's do
it over absolutely I messed it up badly
enough but I should do it
over okay so I think I had blue bar over
here red if I remember I don't remember
red goes through so it stays
red blue bar goes over here and then
turns around so this must be
blue okay this one was blue
bar has to be a quark and an anti-
Quark Blue
Bar straight through blue bar here and
now we have our choice what we want to
put over here so I think I put green
going This
Way
Green Green Green Bar Green goes right
through the
diagram okay now I think it makes
sense every line just goes straight
through red goes straight through that
way Blue Bar goes straight through this
way well we can put the arrow the other
way to indicate anti particle
exchange have to be a cork
antik yeah yeah gluons always have the
properties of Quark
antiquarks earlier you by analogy with
the photons you said the gluons were
massless yeah are these in these
diagrams with all they still
convincingly massless they are
massless we're going to come to what the
meaning of the mass of a quark and a
gluon are all right uh yes they are
massless
um in a technical and special
sense I'll tell you right now what the
special sense
is we're going to quit uh in a minute or
two in fact right now I'll give you an
example we're going to come we're going
to study this Theory one more one more
week and we're going to talk about
confinement of quirks we're going to
talk about the structure of hadrons and
so forth uh but um let me just tell you
in what sense a quark or a gluon does or
does not have a mass or does or does not
have the mass that we ascribe to it so
let me imagine that I have a object of
mass m a small object of mass m and the
small object of mass m has attached to
it a uh I don't know what it is it's
it's whatever you want it to be some
sort of Wiggly soft uh piece of chewing
gum or
something uh that dangles off
it now I want to move this
object if I move the object with a very
small
Force the force being so small that it
doesn't
deform that the acceleration is so slow
that the whole thing moves off
together what kind of mass does it
have the answer is it has the mass of
whatever you put here plus the mass of
the lump of the of the water of chewing
gum or whatever it happens to
be we're thinking now purely
nonrelativistically just to give you an
analogy on the other hand supposing I
shake this thing with a very high
frequency and I ask
um uh what are the properties of the
motion of the uh of the core of it over
here when it's been subjected to a very
very high frequency um force of some
sort what kind of mass does it have over
here just the mass of this object alone
right the rest of it doesn't have time
to uh to adjust to the to the forces it
just stands still now maybe this sends
out a wave all right but the very rapid
oscillation here the response of this
end here would be the response of an
object of mass m so what is the mass of
it is it the mass of the sum of them or
is it the mass of the thing at the end
the answer is ill defined the answer
depends on the frequency of the force
that you uh that you exert on
it masses of objects are frequency
dependent or
well in this sense in this sense the uh
the mass of this object The observed
mass of it that uh that it would respond
with would depend on the frequency of
the motion in the same sense the mass of
a
quark is frequency dependent if you
shake a quark is some kind of object
inside a hadron there are three of them
and there's a bunch of mushy gluon stuff
in there holding them together
okay if you were to try to move the
Quark by itself but if you were trying
to move the Quark slowly if you grabbed
the hole of that cork if you could do so
and you moved it very slowly the whole
thing would drag along and what would be
the mass of it what would be the mass
you would experience the mass of the
whole thing which could be the mass of
the proton which is 930 something or
others what about if you were to uh to
exert a very high frequency force on it
well I'm not going to tell you what well
the answer would be what we normally
call the mass of the Quark that's this
five or 10 uh me for an up or down up or
down Quirk so the mass of the Quirk when
it's subjected to a very very high
frequency or when it's hit very hard and
you try to see how it flies off dragging
this other stuff behind it the initial
impulse that it gets
and the initial velocity that goes off
with will be sensitive to the um to one
value of the mass on the other hand if
you hit it very slowly with a very
gentle low frequency Force the whole
thing would move off so the concept of
what is the mass of a quirk is somewhat
ambiguous uh and to keep the discussion
simple let's say the mass that we
usually ascribe to the for to the Quark
are these high
frequency responses analogous to uh to
the mass at the end of the water chewing
them
here isn't that a restatement of Delta X
delta T not really this is a completely
CL in this case this is a completely
classical phenomenon that uh uh you have
a uh small
little um nut at the end of a uh of a
wiggly something or other you shake it
very rapidly you see it it it
accelerates with one kind of
acceleration you accelerate it with a
low frequency it accelerates different
that's a classical phenomena it does not
have to do with the
uh in the last lecture we described the
electric charge charge electron similar
yes yes yes lesson that's exactly right
the lesson is the parameters that we
describe particles with are dependent on
frequencies and and wavelengths of the
interactions that they engage in they're
called Running con so we say the charge
of a for is
plusus 13 yeah is that is the same story
applies as the case in it does it does
we have to sort out exactly what we mean
by the charge of a quirk but let's just
put it this way it's oneir the charge of
a proton but uh yes you're right we do
have to Define it uh
carefully and that's a whole story unto
itself yeah
yes um why do you always have to have a
quk and an anti-k I can't two for that's
a great question next no no no no that
that's what we're going to talk about we
go that's
next right
yeah this might be to not not the right
time for this question but this all this
uh
stuff with the quarks it's so odd with
the fractional charges and color and I
question is and that because you can't
look at individual CS how do people
figure this out that took time
um yeah well there was a number of Clues
there were a number of
Clues
um by the time I came into physics
the idea of quirks was
already uh established I mean by 19 I I
was a graduate student in
1963 when Murray Gilman announced the
idea of
quarks uh so and I do know how he came
to it but uh
but
the there were Clues there were a lot of
Clues um
there were a lot of Clues but there were
also a lot of
inconsistencies um so it was a pattern
of suggestion suggestive facts together
with apparent inconsistencies such as
the violation of fery statistics and and
there was another fact which was very
peculiar the other fact will come
through next time had to do with the
fact that quirks are never produced in
the laboratory that they're always
permanently confined inside protons
neutrons mesons that was another
fact and uh it wasn't one person who put
it together it was a whole variety of
people who put the whole thing
together nembo had the right idea in the
early 60s he had the right idea but the
whole thing got put together and you
know nailed in place and the whole
structure was uh put together over a
period of 10 years
can you explain why there's only
eight yeah we will talk about that
yeah from from the start this whole
theories is ignoring electrons yes this
theory is ignoring electrons now just
like in Quantum electrodynamics we
ignore
quarks then we have to put them together
we have to put them together into some
coherent thing in
which uh uh quirks and electrons and uh
photons and all of them form one bigger
structure some of which has been done
and some of it has not
been so yeah it is a process of
isolating I mean physics always works
that way you isolate you you you know
you divide and
conquer and then you have to put it all
together okay good let's uh
for more please visit us at stanford.edu